Chapter 114.
The Gilder.
Penetrating further and further into the heart of the Japanese cruising ground,
the Peekquad was soon all a stir in the fishery. Often in mild, pleasant weather
for 12, 15, 18, and 20 hours on the stretch, they were engaged in the boats,
steadily pulling or sailing, or paddling after the whales, or for an interlude of
60 or 70 minutes, calmly awaiting their uprising, though with but small success for their pains.
At such times under an unabated sun, a float all day upon smooth, slow heaving
swells, seated in his boat, light as a birch canoe, and so sociably mixing with
the soft waves themselves, that like hearthstone cats they purr against the
gunnel. These are the times of dreamy quietude, when beholding the tranquil
beauty and brilliancancy of the ocean's skin, one forgets the tiger heart that
pants beneath it, and would not willingly remember that this velvet paw,
but conceals a remorseless fang. These are the times when in his whaleboat the
rover softly feels a certain filial confident landlike feeling towards the
sea that he regards it as so much flowery earth and the distant ship
revealing only the tops of her masts seems struggling forward not through
high rolling waves but through the tall grass of a rolling prairie as when the
western immigrants horses only show their erected ears while their hidden
bodies widely weighed through the amazing virn virgin veils, the mild blue hillsides,
as over these there steals the hush, the hum. You almost swear that playweary
children lie sleeping in these solitudes in some glad Maytime when the flowers of
the woods are plucked, and all this mixes with your most mystic mood, so
that fact and fancy halfway meeting, interpenetrate and form one seamless
hole. Nor did such soothing scenes, however temporary, fail of at least as
temporary an effect on Ahab. But if these secret golden keys did seem to
open in him his own secret golden treasuries, yet did his breath upon them prove but tarnishing.
Oh grassy glades, oh ever vernal endless landscapes in the soul. In ye though
long parched by the dead drought of the earthly life, in ye men yet may roll
like young horses in new morning clover, and for some few fleeting moments feel
the cool dew of the life immortal on them. Would to God these blessed calms
would last. But the mingled mingling threads of life are woven by warp and
woof, calms crossed by storms, a storm for every calm. There is no steady
unretracing progress in this life. We do not advance through fixed gradations,
and at the last one pause, through infancyy's unconscious spell, boyhood's
thoughtless faith, adolescence's doubt, the common doom, then skepticism, then
disbelief, resting at last in manhood's pondering repose of if. But once gone
through, we trace the round again, and our infants, boys, and men, and ifs
eternally. Where lies the final harbor, whence we unore no more? In what wrapped
ether sails the world, of which the weariest will never weary? Where is the
foundling's father hidden? Our souls are like those orphans whose unwed mothers
die in bearing them. The secret of our paternity lies in their grave, and we
must dare to learn it.
And that same day, too, gazing far down from his boat's side into that same
golden sea, Starbucks lowly murmured, loveliness unfathomable, as ever lover
saw in his young bride's eye, "Tell me not of thy teeths, and thy kidnapping
cannibal ways. Let faith oust fact. Let fancy oust memory. I look deep down and do believe.
And Stub, fishlike with sparkling scales, leaped up in that same golden
light. I am Stub, and Stub has his history. But here, Stub takes oaths that
he has always been jolly.